### ANTONIO A. FIERRO, Ed.D.

#### **SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS**

Accomplished, versatile educational leader with extensive experience in consulting, project management, university instruction, and educational training. Experienced in all facets of the Tier III Reading Model, linguistics, bilingual education, and child development with a strong focus on professional training in various mediums including classrooms, workshops, and national conferences. Advanced involvement in the research, diagnostic approach, and development for dyslexic student programs. Proficient in coordinating, executing, and supervising action plans for multimillion dollar educational grants. Possess excellent written and verbal communication skills in staff development, student training, and public presentation; highly capable of directing multiple individuals of various professional levels.

### **CORE COMPETENCIES:**

- Personnel Director / Manager
- Teaching Practices / Methodologies
- Grant Management / Budgeting
- Bilingual / Linguistics Reading Consultation
- Three Tier Reading Model Application
- · Educator / Reading Coach Training
- Educational Research / Analysis
- Dual Language Program Management

National Trainer of Language Essentials for Teacher of Reading and Spelling (LETRS); Bilingual in English and Spanish

#### **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Education in Educational Leadership and Administration University of Texas, El Paso, Texas

Master of Education in Elementary Education Sul Ross State University, Alpine, Texas

Bachelor of Business Administration in Marketing and Management University of Texas, El Paso, Texas

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Principal's Certificate, 2006

Gifted and Talented Endorsement, 1997

Endorsements for Early Childhood, Bilingual Education, and English as a Second Language, 1991

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### READING CONSULTANT INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

2007 - Present National Assignments

- Serve as a national consultant in a broad educational spectrum as a member of the professional development program LETRS (Language Essentials for Teachers of Reading and Spelling) led by Dr. Louisa C. Moats; provided consulting guidance to the Texas Education Agency, lowa and South Carolina Departments of Education, and Bureau of Indian Education.
- Specialize in research for phonological awareness, phonemic awareness, dyslexia, dyslexia and the older student, vocabulary, and the English language learner; provide professional consulting services in areas of reading, instruction, and bilingual/ESL education.
- Contributing author to Pearson/Scott Foresman's Reading Street program; also advised
  publication teams and reviewed material regarding those approaches appropriate for the
  English Language Learner and the correct implementation of Spanish linguistic properties.
- Recognized as a featured speaker at various national conferences regarding research in areas of reading, bilingual education, language arts and content areas; discuss the implementation of dual language programs and instructional dynamics; consult on proper execution of the Three Tier Reading Model and literacy activities in the classroom.

ANTONIO A. FIERRO PAGE TWO

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE** (Continued...)

# ADJUNCT PROFESSOR 2002 – Present UT, EL PASO / UC, COLORADO SPRINGS / NM STATE UNIVERSITY National Assignments

 Provided instruction in undergraduate, graduate, and alternative certifications in the College of Education focusing on early reading foundations, diagnostic assessment of reading, dyslexia, child development, bilingual education, and the struggling older reader.

- Prepared curriculum and educational materials for pre-service teachers; administered classroom instruction and supervisory guidance as they provided tutoring for students ranging from kindergarten to high school and students attending the University Reading Camp.
- Engaged in online education corresponding with students on various technology platforms including online video lectures, electronic testing/homework assignments, and interactive chat room sessions.

### COORDINATOR / DIRECTOR, READING FIRST EL PASO INDEPENDENT SCHOOL DISTRICT

2005 - 2006 El Paso, Texas

- Monitored implementation of a \$3.8M Reading First grant budget in collaboration with the Texas Department of Education and the Texas Education Agency serving as a liaison between school, district, and training centers to ensure proper execution of budget plan; identified areas of opportunity and restructured grant distribution as needed.
- Interviewed, hired, and trained a staff of 30 training coaches; coordinated with state Reading Technical Assistance specialists to provide supplemental training; mentored district administrators to improve on the implementation of the Three Tier Reading Model.
- Identified subcommittees to provide a needs assessment for Tier II instruction, data analysis
  and interpretation, and a scope and sequence for all new coaches; monitored and analyzed
  district data to provide targeted reading instruction at all three tiers of the model.
- Collaborated with Special Education departments to identify needs for Tier III Instruction; coauthored the assessment process for the identification of the dyslexic Tier III student.

### SENIOR FIELD TRAINING ANALYST VAUGHN GROSS CENTER FOR READING AND LANGUAGE ARTS

2005 Austin, Texas

- Provided technical assistance, conducted site research/analysis, and assisted with site budget planning for various education agencies in the central United States under the direction of a large scale, national education center.
- Developed instructional delivery plans targeting professional development, consistent state
  and district funding, and capacity building; mentored teachers in implementing Reading First
  components; helped establish action plans for differentiated instruction, intervention, fidelity to
  the core reading program, and the Three Tier Reading Model.
- Served as a National Reading Academy trainer for teachers grades K-4 emphasizing on the five critical components of reading; trained on the best practices for English Language Learners including pedagogy, vocabulary development, comprehension strategies, and linguistic properties of the English language.
- Presented "Scientifically Based Reading Research and English Language Learners: The Big Picture" at the National Reading First Conference in Louisiana; mentored teachers in Chicago Public Schools in the administration of DIBELS workshop.

## PROGRAM MANAGER REGION 19 EDUCATION SERVICE CENTER

2000 - 2005 El Paso, Texas

- Managed and coordinated a \$2M Texas Reading Initiative grant for the Region 19 area that included 12 school local districts and two charter schools; supervised a staff of 15 professionals ensuring the proper execution of the area's professional development plan.
- Oversaw the \$100K Accelerated Reading Instruction grant targeting reading interventions for struggling readers; assisted in the development of dyslexia plans for various districts; wrote professional modules focusing on reading fluency, early identification with dyslexic students, diagnostic testing phonological awareness and reading academies.

ANTONIO A. FIERRO PAGE THREE

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE** (Continued...)

Served as regional academy trainer and led workshops and seminars for approximately 1,500 Pre-K through 4<sup>th</sup> grade teachers in scientifically based research and instruction; served as 2<sup>nd</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> grade state Master Trainer for the Teacher Reading Academies emphasizing phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary, fluency, and comprehension.

 Contributed to the establishment of norms for the Indicadores Dinámicos del Éxito en la Lectura (IDEL) at the Canutillo Independent School District; function as the Instructional Leadership Development Trainer/Presenter for a wide scope of administrators.

### TEACHER / BILINGUAL SPECIALIST SOCORRO INDEPENDENT SCHOOL DISTRICT

1993 - 2000 El Paso, Texas

- Instructed kindergarten and 1<sup>st</sup> grade students in a dual language curriculum focusing on early childhood, reading, gifted and talented, and bilingual education; maintained positive learning environment and conducted individual evaluations to gauge student progress.
- Credited with authoring and designing the district's first dual language program, "Power, Promise, and Prosperity."

#### **HONORS/AWARDS**

Texas Elementary Teacher of the Year and Texas Representative to the National Teacher of the Year Competition, 1996

Region 19 Elementary Teacher of the Year, 1996

Outstanding Teacher of Reading, El Paso Reading Association, 1997

# LANGUAGE ESSENTIALS FOR TEACHERS OF READING AND SPELLING (LETRS)

Initial LETRS training of modules 1-12	2000 – 2005
Presenter of LETRS sessions, Modules 1-12	2006 - Pres
Attended LETRS TOT sessions presented by Carol Tolman and Nancy Hennessey	2013 - 2014
Presenter of initial and TOT sessions	2014 - Pres

### **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

International Dyslexia Association Association of Hispanic School Administrators International Reading Association Kappa Delta Pi Texas Association for Bilingual Education

### ANTONIO A. FIERRO, Ed.D.

1632 Rock Dove Ln. El Paso, Texas 79911 Mobile: (915) 274-7814 aafierro\_20@yahoo.com

### **PROFESSIONAL REFERENCES**

### Dr. Louisa Moats, Author and Researcher

Moats Associates Consulting, Inc. P.O. Box 6193 Sun Valley, ID 83354 (208) 720-9096

### Dr. Roland Good, Author and Researcher

Dynamic Measurement Group 859 Willamette Street, Suite 320 Eugene, OR 97401 (541) 431-6931

### Dr. Gary Brooks, Emeritus Professor in Educational Leadership Foundations

University of Texas at El Paso 2138 Radford Street (217) 328-9917

### Dr. John Slate, Professor in Education Leadership

Sam Houston State University Huntsville, Texas 77341 (936) 294-1147

### Dr. Anna Lisa Banegas-Peña, Superintendent

Retired 312 Windrose Place El Paso, Texas 79912 (915) 433-1983